Guide to the Ulrich Bonnell Phillips Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ulrich Bonnell Phillips papers
1712-1933
1800-1861
MS 397
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
25.75
(52 boxes)
The papers consist of the research files of Ulrich Bonnell Phillips, an author and history professor. The papers include Phillips's notes and transcripts of historical source materials and the collected papers of several southern families from 1712-1933. The collected papers include correspondence, account books, business records, farm and plantation records, diaries, photographs, and other papers which focus primarily on the years 1790-1865, and the Shenandoah Valley region of Virginia and the Piedmont region of Georgia. Phillips's own papers in the collection include a small amount of correspondence, lecture notes, typescript versions of published essays and reviews, transcripts of materials from various sources, his research notes arranged by topic, and related printed matter.
Phillips, Ulrich Bonnell, 1877-1934
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Access is to glass slides and negatives is restricted for preservation purposes. Researchers must use digital surrogates available in the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database (MADID).
Existence and Location of Copies
All of the glass slides and negatives and many of the other photographic images have been digitally reproduced and are available through the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database (MADID).
Additional information not yet available in the online version of the finding aid exists in the repository. Contact Manuscripts and Archives for assistance.
Separated Materials
Original nitrate negatives were removed from the collection and destroyed following digitization.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the material was purchased from the estate of U. B. Phillips in 1934. There was also a gift of additional material by Mrs. Phillips and David M. Potter in 1961. Transfer from the Peabody Museum of Natural History, Yale University, 2006.
Arrangement
Arranged in eighteen series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1748-1961. II. Records, Bonds, and Accounts, 1753-1882. III. Account Books and Diaries, 1812-1899. IV. Pamphlets, 1712-1918. V. Bryan Family, 1828-1883. VI. Cabell-Hare Family, 1792-1825. VII. Dorman Family, 1821-1881. VIII. McDowell Family, 1792-1861. IX. Moore Family, 1794-1865. X. Newton-Steele Family, 1803-1864. XI. Reid Family, 1758-1867. XII. Thomas Family, 1849-1888. XIII. Willson Family, 1806-1869. XIV. Walker Family, 1818-1847. XV. Transcripts. XVI. Manuscripts, 1904-1939. XVII. Research Notes. XVIII. Miscellanea.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of the research files of Ulrich Bonnell Phillips, an author and history professor. The papers include Phillips's notes and transcripts of historical source materials and the collected papers of several southern families from 1712-1933. The collected papers include correspondence, account books, business records, farm and plantation records, diaries, photographs, and other papers which focus primarily on the years 1790-1865, and the Shenandoah Valley region of Virginia and the Piedmont region of Georgia. Phillips's own papers in the collection include a small amount of correspondence, lecture notes, typescript versions of published essays and reviews, transcripts of materials from various sources, his research notes arranged by topic, and related printed matter.
Biographical / Historical
Ulrich Bonnell Phillips was born in La Grange, Louisiana, on November 4, 1887. He taught history at several universities, including Yale University (1929-1934). He specialized in southern history, collected primary source material, and published extensively on the subject. Phillips died in New Haven, Connecticut, on January 21, 1934.
Publication Note
Reproductions of photographs from Accession 2007-M-012 were published in
Bixel, Patricia Bellis, and John David Smith. Seeing the New South: Race and Place in the Photographs of Ulrich BonnellPhillips. Columbia, SC: University of South Carolina Press, 2013.
Slavery -- United States; Georgia; Southern States; United States -- History -- 1783-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Virginia; Account books; Diaries; Educators; Historians; Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943; Benton, Thomas Hart, 1782-1858; Breckinridge, James, 1763-1833; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Cobb, Howell, 1815-1868; Cobb, Mary Ann Lamar; Dorman, James Baldwin, 1823-1893; Massie, Thomas, 1748-1834; Massie, William, 1795-1862; McDowell, Alexander Marshall; McDowell, James, 1770-1835; McDowell, James, 1795-1851; McDowell, James, d. 1814; McDowell, John Adair, 1789-1823; McDowell, Joseph, 1768-1856; McDowell, Samuel, 1764-; Mitchell, David Brydie, 1766-1837; Mitchell, Sarah Caroline Neisler; Moore, Andrew, 1752-1821; Moore, Samuel McDowell, 1796-1875; Phillips, Ulrich Bonnell, 1877-1934; Reid, Andrew, fl, 1805-1811; Reid, Andrew, 1751-1837; Reid, Samuel McDowell, 1790-1869; Smith, Isaac, 1829-; Steele, Robert, 1860-1944; Stephens, Alexander H. (Alexander Hamilton), 1812-1883; Toombs, Robert Augustus, 1810-1885; Troup, George Michael, 1780-1856; Turner, Frederick Jackson, 1861-1932; Williams, Samuel May, 1795-1858; Willson, Elizabeth Ann; Bryant family; Cable family; Dorman family; Hair family; McDowell family; Moore family; Newton family; Reed family; Steele family; Thomas family; Walker family; Wilson family; Virginia infantry. 6th regt., 1776-1778; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1748-1961; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the letters of several individuals and families including: Thomas and Lizzie Armentrout, merchant-farmers in Virginia (bulk dates 1865-92); the Douglass family of Virginia and Missouri (1808-49); Henry St. George Harris, a planter from Virginia (1846-66); and William Letcher Mitchell, chief engineer of the Western and Atlantic Railroad in Georgia (1830-82). Letters to and from several other individuals who lived in the southern United States in the nineteenth century are also included in this series.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  - 1748-1830 (Box 1, Folder 1-24)
  - 1831-1849 (Box 2, Folder 25-43)
  - 1850-1879 (Box 3, Folder 44-71)
  - 1880-1910 (Box 4, Folder 72-77)
  - 1911-1961 (Box 5, Folder 78-82)
- Records, bonds, and accounts, 1753-1882; Series II
  The series consists of promissory notes, bonds of indebtedness, court records, and accounting volumes. Material of George Rochfort, a merchant from Athens, Georgia (1795-1817) and John Robinson, a whiskey and cloth merchant from Lexington, Virginia (1805-1826) are included in this series. Other items also arranged here include a diary (1857-58) of Richard M. Venable of Virginia, and business and household accounts of Jesse Scott (1821-36), Richard V. Tiffey (1835-37), Thomas Massie (1748-98), Howell and Mary Ann Lamar Cobb (1840-42), and William Letcher Mitchell (1823-29).
  - 1753-1826 (Box 6, Folder 83-100)
  - 1827-1882 and undated (Box 7, Folder 101-117)
- Account books and diaries, 1812-1899; Series III
  The series contains diaries of William and Sarah Mitchell (1823-30) and account books of Mary Ann and Howell Cobb (1840-42), among others.
  This series contains material arranged in chronological order by type of item.
  - Diary (correspondence) of William and Sarah Mitchell, 1823-1830 (Box 8, Folder 118)
  - Diary of Richard M. Venable, 1857-1858 (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - Diary pages of Ulrich Bonnell Phillips, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 119A)
    The two diary pages describe a visit to Paris, August 18-19, and the itinerary for a trip to Europe in July and August.
  - Richard V. Tiffey: Daybook of King George Court House, 1835-1837 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Mary Ann Cobb's Account Books, 1840-1842 (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Howell Cobb's Account Book, 1841 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - John Irvine, Receipt book, 1812-1814 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Account Books and Diary general store, farm and cash accounts, 1821-1836 (Box 47, Folder 6)
- Pamphlets, 1712-1918; Series IV
  This series contains a group of published items which focuses on political issues in the southern United States (ca1850-65). Published speeches and addresses by major political figures are included, and certain items are photostatic copies of original documents.
  The pamphlets and a small quantity of clippings in this series are arranged in chronological order.
  - Pamphlets, 1712-1908 and undated (Box 9, Folder 124-139)
  - Clippings, 1807-1918 (Box 9, Folder 140)
- Bryan family, 1828-1883; Series V
  This series consists of contracts, correspondence, business papers, and other material relating to Matthew Bryan's iron works operation in Virginia and to his sons' college years at Washington College and the University of Virginia.
  This series contains material arranged in chronological order.
  - 1828-1883 and undated (Box 10, Folder 141-149)
- Cabell-Hare family, 1792-1825; Series VI
  This series consists of account books, correspondence, and papers documenting the lives of William B. Hare (1760-1818), a physician and landowner, and his descendants. These papers contain information on the economic, social, and political activity in the tidewater region of Virginia, and documentation on tobacco and wheat farming, plantation life, medical practice, slavery, and local merchants. A diary of Philip Rootes (1792 Nov-Dec) is also included in this series.
  - 1792-1825 and undated (Box 11, Folder 150-166)
- Dorman family, 1821-1881; Series VII
  This series contains correspondence and papers of James Baldwin Dorman (1823-1893), a lawyer, Virginia state legislator, and member of the 1861 Secession Convention. Photostatic copies of papers of James Dorman Davidson, which Phillips obtained from the McCormick Agricultural Library in Chicago, Illinois are also included in this series. Dorman correspondence during the 1840s, and his diary (1841-49) detail his student life at Washington College, and his experiences as a school teacher, traveller, and soldier during the Mexican War. Letters from Dorman's parents, Charles P. and Amanda Elizabeth McCue Dorman, detail family matters.
  - 1821-1861 (Box 12, Folder 168-185)
  - 1862-1881 and undated (Box 13, Folder 186-190)
- McDowell Family, 1792-1861; Series VIII
  This series consists of correspondence and papers documenting the lives of family members in Virginia, Kentucky, Missouri, and elsewhere. Family members represented in this series include: James McDowell (1770-1835), a farmer with extensive land holdings in Virginia and Kentucky, a prominent figure in the state militia during the War of 1812, and the father-in-law of Thomas Hart Benton, the Missouri senator whose four letters refer to political topics; James McDowell (1795-1851), a student at Yale College who left a two thousand acre plantation in Kentucky given to him by his father in order to enter Virginia politics as a Democrat. Few political papers detail his activity as a state legislator (1830-38), governor (1843-46), and Congressman (1846-51). Other family members represented to lesser degrees in this series include: James McDowell, a Kentucky physician, and Samuel McDowell and his descendents.
  - 1792-1861 and undated (Box 14, Folder 191-203)
- Moore family, 1794-1865; Series IX
  This series consists of correspondence and papers of Andrew Moore (1752-1821), a representative (1789-99) and senator (1800-09) from Virginia, and Samuel McDowell Moore (1796-1876), a lawyer educated at Washington College who served in the Virginia General Assembly (1825-47), and as a congressman (1833-35). He also campaigned unsuccessfully for governor, and attended the Constitutional Convention of 1829-1830 and the Secession Convention of 1861. Andrew Moore's letters comment on the Embargo and Non-intercourse incidents during the years 1807-1812. Samuel McDowell Moore's letters include references to political and family matters.
  - 1794-1865 and undated (Box 15, Folder 204-210)
- Newton-Steele family, 1803-1864; Series X
  This series consists of the papers of John Newton and Robert Steele, brothers-in-law and tradesmen in Virginia. Newton was a hatter, farmer, and justice of the peace, and his papers include several items relating to his official duties as magistrate. Steele was a dry goods merchant whose financial difficulties led him to emigrate to Missouri. His death in the 1840s and the subsequent plight of his family is detailed in letters written by Steele's widow to Newton.
  - 1803-1864 (Box 16, Folder 111-124)
- Reid family, 1758-1867; Series XI
  This series consists of correspondence, account books, land and legal records, and related papers of several family members in Virginia. Andrew Reid (1751-1837) was a farmer, clerk of the county court, and clerk of the circuit court. His papers include court records, bonds, official documents, and extensive correspondence relating to agricultural matters. Another Andrew Reid (fl. 1805-11) appears as a correspondent in 1805 and, in letters dating through 1811, Reid discusses experiences as a Virginia legislator and as a young lawyer. His extensive correspondence with Samuel McDowell Reid and former Washington College classmates includes mention of family and political affairs, such as the Burr Conspiracy. Samuel McDowell Reid, who succeeded his father Andrew as clerk of the county and superior courts also served in the Virginia legislature during the Civil War, ran a large legal practice, supervised four major estates, managed family lands in the west, and served as a trustee for Washington College. Correspondence documents his activity as a lawyer, businessman, legislator, and plantation manager. Reid frequently dealt with the issue of slavery in his business dealings, and it is a common topic in his letters.
  This series is arranged in two sections: Financial accounts and Correspondence. Financial accounts files are arranged alphabetically and Correspondence files are arranged chronologically.
  - Financial accounts
    - Massie, Thomas, 1776-1798 (Box 17, Folder 125-126)
    - Reid, Andrew, Sr., 1758-1772 (Box 17, Folder 127-128)
    - Reid, Andrew, Jr., 1772-1780 (Box 17, Folder 129)
    - Reid, Samuel McDowell, 1821-1858 (Box 17, Folder 130-132)
    - Robinson, John, 1775-1811 (Box 17, Folder 133-134)
  - Correspondence
    - 1787-1861 (Box 18, Folder 135-155)
    - 1862-1867 and undated (Box 19, Folder 156-159)
- Thomas family, 1849-1888; Series XII
  This series consists of the correspondence and papers of Thomas W. Thomas, a lawyer in Elberton, Georgia, and active in Democratic politics until 1850, when he joined with Howell Cobb, Robert Toombs, and Alexander H. Stephens to form the Constitutional Union Party of Georgia. He later became a judge in the state superior court and a colonel in the Confederate army. Correspondence details Thomas's legal and financial affairs, and includes letters from many minor Georgia political figures and other family members.
  This series contains material arranged chronologically.
  - 1849-1888 and undated (Box 20, Folder 160-167)
- Willson family, 1806-1869; Series XIII
  This series consists of correspondence, financial records, and papers relating to the land holdings and farming activities of Thomas Willson, a Virginia and Indiana farmer. Correspondence with his Indiana agents: Thomas McClure, Arthur Compton, and John Buntain document more than thirty years of agricultural activity. Willson's letters with his brother William B., an Ohio physician, also focus on farming matters.
  The remaining papers document the lives of the children and grandchildren of James S. Willson, a brother of Thomas and William B. Willson. Elizabeth Ann Willson, an unmarried daughter, and two sons, William Finley Willson, another Ohio physician, and Thomas Newton Willson, a schoolteacher, discuss abolitionist views, pro-slavery sentiments, and family, economic, and political matters with each other and their father James.
  - 1806-1860 (Box 21, Folder 168-186)
  - 1861-1869 and undated (Box 22, Folder 187-192)
- Walker family, 1818-1847; Series XIV
  This series consists of correspondence among members of the Walker family in Virginia and relatives in the South and West. Joseph and John B. Walker comment on Missouri land speculations, Hugh and James C. Walker detail life in Tennessee, William and Sam Walker detail life at Princeton, and Henry Brown writes of his preaching experiences in the Kanawha Valley.
  - 1818-1847 (Box 23, Folder 193-201)
- Transcripts, 1783-1868; Series XV
  This series consists of Ulrich B. Phillips' research notes relating to southern history. Phillips transcribed historical sources in academic institutions, libraries, and private sources. Selected portions of these transcripts appeared in such published works as The Correspondence of Robert Toombs, Alexander H. Stephens, and Howell Cobb. Most of the material in this series is undated; specific dates are noted at the file level below only when known.
  This series is arranged in four sections: General, Plantations, Politics, and Transportation. Each section is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - General
    - Agriculture (Box 24, Folder 202)
    - American Revolution (Box 24, Folder 203)
    - Artisans and town labor (Box 24, Folder 204)
    - Banking (Box 24, Folder 205)
    - Black Cross (Box 24, Folder 206)
    - Civil War period (Box 24, Folder 207)
    - Commerce - wagon trade (Box 24, Folder 208)
    - Cotton (Box 24, Folder 209)
    - Crisis of 1837-1839 (Box 24, Folder 210)
    - Desperadoes (Box 24, Folder 211)
    - Domestic service (Box 24, Folder 212)
    - Duels (Box 24, Folder 213)
    - Economics of slavery in the South (Box 25, Folder 214)
    - Education (Box 25, Folder 215)
    - Emancipation (Box 25, Folder 216)
    - Factors (Box 25, Folder 217)
    - Financial crisis (Box 25, Folder 218)
    - Fortunes (of the Confederate people) in war (Box 25, Folder 219)
    - Free Negroes (Box 25, Folder 220)
    - Frontier (Box 25, Folder 221)
    - Georgia colony (Box 25, Folder 222)
    - Georgia history (Box 25, Folder 223)
    - Georgia politics (Box 25, Folder 224)
    - Georgia, University of (Box 25, Folder 225)
    - Immigration (Box 26, Folder 226)
    - Indentured servants (Box 26, Folder 227)
    - Industrial society in the North (Box 26, Folder 228)
    - Iron Manufacture, Virginia (Box 26, Folder 229)
    - Iron works (Box 26, Folder 230)
    - Labor organizations (Box 26, Folder 231)
    - Jefferson (Thomas) on slavery (Box 26, Folder 232)
    - Johnson, Andrew - 1860 (Box 26, Folder 233)
    - Kentucky records (Box 26, Folder 234)
    - Know-Nothings (Box 26, Folder 235)
    - Land speculations (Box 26, Folder 236)
    - Legal provisions concerning industrial society (Box 26, Folder 237)
    - Louisiana (Box 26, Folder 238)
    - Manufactures in the South (Box 26, Folder 239)
    - Maryland Colony (Box 26, Folder 240)
    - Migration (Box 26, Folder 241)
    - Miscellaneous: letters (Box 26, Folder 242)
    - Miscellaneous: politics, 1760-1877 (Box 26, Folder 243)
    - Miscellaneous: social and economic (Box 27, Folder 244)
    - Mississippi River navigation (Box 27, Folder 245)
    - Negro crime (Box 27, Folder 246)
    - Negro slavery (Box 27, Folder 247)
    - Negroes: 1865-1868 (Box 27, Folder 248)
    - New Orleans (Box 27, Folder 249)
    - Non-agricultural pursuits of slaves and freedmen (Box 27, Folder 250)
    - North Carolina Colony (Box 27, Folder 251)
    - Nullification (Box 27, Folder 252)
    - Original MSS: unclassified (Box 27, Folder 253)
    - Overseers (Box 27, Folder 254)
    - Plantation (Box 27, Folder 255)
    - Plantation economics (Box 27, Folder 256)
    - Plantation labor (Box 28, Folder 257)
    - Plantation life (Box 28, Folder 258)
    - Plantation management (Box 28, Folder 259)
    - Plantations (Box 28, Folder 260)
    - Prices current (Box 28, Folder 261)
    - Poor whites (Box 28, Folder 262)
    - Rice and indigo (Box 28, Folder 263)
    - Runaway slaves (Box 28, Folder 264)
    - Secession (Box 28, Folder 265)
    - Slave hiring (Box 28, Folder 266)
    - Slave insurrection (Box 28, Folder 267)
    - Slave prices (Box 29, Folder 268)
    - Slave stealing (Box 29, Folder 269)
    - Slave trade (Box 29, Folder 270)
    - Slave trade (African) re-opening (Box 29, Folder 271)
    - Slavery in politics (Box 29, Folder 272)
    - Slavery, plantation, etc., in the tropics (Box 29, Folder 273)
    - Slavery (anti and pro) sentiment (Box 29, Folder 274)
    - Slavery: West Indies (Box 29, Folder 275)
    - Society (Box 29, Folder 276)
    - South Carolina Colony (Box 30, Folder 277)
    - Southern Industrial Society: transcripts, notes, outline for Plantation and Frontier (Box 30, Folder 278)
    - Southeast (Box 30, Folder 279)
  - Plantations
    - Belmead plantation records (Box 30, Folder 280)
    - Lamar, J.B. plantation records (Box 30, Folder 281)
    - Manigault plantation records (Box 30, Folder 282)
    - Organized labour (Box 30, Folder 283)
    - Rules for the management and medical treatment of slaves (Box 30, Folder 284)
    - Salley: letters (Box 30, Folder 285)
    - Sugar crops (Box 30, Folder 286)
    - Telfair manuscripts (Box 31, Folder 287)
    - Virginia slave crime vouchers (Box 31, Folder 288)
  - Politics
    - Alabama: Montgomery Daily Mail (Box 31, Folder 289)
    - Camp meetings (Box 31, Folder 290)
    - Crawford, William Harris; newspaper excerpts (Box 31, Folder 291)
    - Cobb, Howell on the Confederacy, 1862 (Box 31, Folder 292)
    - Crisis of 1850 (Box 31, Folder 293)
    - Crittenden correspondence, 1838-1860 (Box 31, Folder 294-96)
    - Kansas-Nebraska (Box 31, Folder 297)
    - "Louisiana Politics", 1804 (Box 31, Folder 298)
    - Massie Mss, description of, Univ. of Texas (Box 31, Folder 299)
    - Pickett, Albert James papers (Box 31, Folder 300)
    - Social Relations, Hundley, 1860 (Box 31, Folder 301)
    - South Carolina "Appius", 1794 (Box 32, Folder 302)
    - South Carolina, The Charleston Morning Post, 1786 (Box 32, Folder 303)
    - Southern nationalization (Box 32, Folder 304)
    - Toombs, Stephens: Cobb correspondence, 1840-1864 (Box 32, Folder 305-311)
    - Travel (Box 32, Folder 312)
      - Travel in the West, 1845 (Box 32, Folder 313)
      - Williams papers (Box 32, Folder 314)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 32, Folder 315)
  - Transportation
    - Georgia
      - Atlanta Commerce to 1861 (Box 32, Folder 316)
      - Georgia and S. Carolina railroads (Box 32, Folder 317)
      - Internal improvements (Box 32, Folder 318)
      - Navigations (Box 32, Folder 319)
      - Trade centers (Box 32, Folder 320)
      - Travellers accounts (Box 32, Folder 321)
      - Union-states rights, 1959-1961 (Box 32, Folder 322)
      - Whigs (Box 32, Folder 323)
    - N. Carolina internal improvements, 1834 (Box 32, Folder 324)
    - Railroads
      - General (Box 32, Folder 325)
      - Conventions (Box 33, Folder 326)
      - State aid (Box 33, Folder 327)
      - Western and Atlantic, 1865-1868 (Box 33, Folder 328)
    - South Carolina
      - Hamburg (Box 33, Folder 329)
      - Railroad policy (Box 33, Folder 330)
      - Transportation (Box 33, Folder 331)
    - Tobacco (Box 33, Folder 332)
    - Traffic in indentured servants (Box 33, Folder 333)
    - Transportation (Box 33, Folder 334)
    - Virginia
      - 1783-1860 (Box 33, Folder 335)
      - Internal improvements (Box 33, Folder 336)
      - Colony (Box 33, Folder 337)
    - West Indies depression (Box 33, Folder 338)
    - Whigs and Democrats (Box 33, Folder 339)
- Manuscripts, 1904-1939; Series XVI
  This series contains drafts of published and unpublished writings by Phillips and others.
  This series is arranged in two sections: Phillips, Ulrich Bonnell, and Others. Each section is arranged in chronological order.